Boker Tov (בוקר טוב), Boker Tov today's daf (דף) daf is Kof
Mem Hey (קמ״ה) Kof Mem Hey 145. We pick up and
we pick up about let's see about ten lines down where it
says U'veplugta (ובפלוגתא); U'veplugta the line starts with the word Lav Mashkeh
Hu (לאו משקה הוא). Lav Mashkeh Hu And the current debate is
we've been saying that you can squeeze fruit into food, actually it
sounds like maybe even into a pot that's going into food, but
certainly directly into food. And the Gemara (גמרא) Gemara has said that
there is a debate about whether wanting to say maybe this is
a debate whether Mashkeh Haba Le'ochel (משקה הבא לאוכל) Mashkeh Haba Le'ochel
is considered Ochel (אוכל) Ochel or not and looking at comparisons to
definitions of Mashkeh (משקה) Mashkeh for Tuma V'tahara (טומאה וטהרה). Tuma V'tahara
And then the Gemara (גמרא) Gemara said yesterday not necessarily maybe that
the case that it was looking at, thank you, where you smeared
grape juice on the crust, the surface of bread, maybe that was
considered that was Mashkeh (משקה) Mashkeh going for Ibud (איבוד) Ibud and
that's why, but otherwise maybe it would have a status of Mashkeh
(משקה) Mashkeh even though it was heading for food. So now the
Gemara (גמרא) Gemara is going to say about again ten lines down,
line starting with the word Lav Mashkeh Hu (לאו משקה הוא), Lav
Mashkeh Hu it says U'veplugta De'hanei Tanna'ei (ובפלוגתא דהני תנאי) U'veplugta De'hanei
Tanna'ei and it seems to be the same as this debate of
Tanna'im (תנאים). Tanna'im Detanya (דתניא), Detanya we taught in a Braisa (ברייתא),
Braisa Ha'mifatze'a Bezaysim Beyadayim Mesovos (המפצע בזיתים בידיים מסואבות), Ha'mifatze'a Bezaysim Beyadayim
Mesovos if somebody basically crushes, squeezes out olives with hands that are
Tamei (טמא), Tamei Huchshar (הוכשר), Huchshar then they have
become susceptible for becoming Tamei (טמא) Tamei because the olives themselves
have the liquid from the olives have themselves made the olives Huchshar
(הוכשר), Huchshar made the olives susceptible. Okay, now the reason you're squeezing
it is to make them softer and
tastier, but apparently the olive oil that comes out you want it
because that helps in the taste. So this is a case where
you wanted the liquid and it came out and therefore it made
the olives susceptible. What?
You touched the liquid? Is that it?
It doesn't matter, you touch the food and the food touches the
liquid. Okay, so Huchshar (הוכשר). Huchshar Lesafotan Bemelach (לספותן במלח), Lesafotan Bemelach
however, if you are crushing the olives because you want
to basically soften them so that you can dip them in salt,
okay, but you're not really doing it that the softening is improving
the taste, it's just making it able to be dipped in salt,
then you're really not interested in the liquid that comes out
and Lo Huchshar (לא הוכשר), Lo Huchshar then it does not become
susceptible because the liquid that comes out is not considered Mashkeh (משקה).
Mashkeh Okay, so far that's a principle that liquids only make things
susceptible if you are if you want them. Now, actually wanting them
is in two directions: one is wanting them like we learned on
Shabbos (שבת) Shabbos that difficult discussion about milking and so on, you
want them actually to be produced and that's sometimes in ambiguous cases
is needed to give it a Shem Mashkeh (שם משקה). Shem Mashkeh
The other situation is when you want them on the object that
they actually have touched. Anyway, here's what's relevant to us: Lada'at Im
Higiu Zaysim Limsok (לדעת אם הגיעו זיתים למסוק) Lada'at Im Higiu Zaysim
Limsok Im Lav (אם לאו), Im Lav Lo Huchshar (לא הוכשר). Lo
Huchshar If you're doing it in order to know whether your olives
are ready for harvesting, so you squeeze out a little juice so
you just want to see how ripe they are, then it is
not Huchshar (הוכשר) Huchshar because then you really don't want, again you're
not really interested in the liquid, you're interested in testing how ripe
it is. But we'll see in a minute how the Gemara (גמרא)
Gemara is going to frame it, okay, because in a way you
actually do want to see are they ripe enough that the oil
come out easily with squeezing. Rebbi Yehuda Omer Huchshar (רבי יהודה אומר
הוכשר), Rebbi Yehuda Omer Huchshar it has become susceptible. So what's that
debate? I mean, you want the oil to come out to see
if it's able to how ripe the olive is. So Mai Lav
Be'ha Kamipligi (מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי), Mai Lav Be'ha Kamipligi it must
be the following debate: Mar Savar Mashkeh Omad Le'ibud Mashkeh Hu (מר
סבר משקה עומד לאיבוד משקה הוא), Mar Savar Mashkeh Omad Le'ibud Mashkeh
Hu one says because they both agree you want it, however the
issue is is that it's being squeezed straight on the ground, you're
not preserving it, but you want it to come out to test
the ripeness of the olive. So one says if it's going Le'ibud
(לאיבוד) Le'ibud to waste, it's still is a Mashkeh (משקה) Mashkeh and
it makes the thing susceptible, and Mar Savar Lav Mashkeh Hu (ומר
סבר לאו משקה הוא) Mar Savar Lav Mashkeh Hu it's not. Okay,
so therefore since there's that debate normally we assume that maybe that's
also the debate of smearing the grapes on the surface of the
bread, although it's funny to call that Le'ibud (לאיבוד) Le'ibud and the
Gemara (גמרא) Gemara will qualify that in a minute, but maybe again
the Gemara (גמרא) Gemara is saying that even if it's going to
food it's considered food and the whole issue is when it's going
Le'ibud (לאיבוד). Le'ibud Yes.
How can someone something Mekabel Tuma (מקבל טומאה) Mekabel Tuma when it
hasn't even been harvested yet?
Oh, that's a good point. Maybe you pluck one and you squeeze
it to see whether the others are fit for harvesting or the
oil is still on it when you harvest. But excellent point, while
it's still attached it would not be Huchshar (הוכשר). Huchshar Okay. So
now the Gemara (גמרא) Gemara says like this: Amar Rav Huna Brei
De'Rav Yehoshua (אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע), Amar Rav Huna Brei
De'Rav Yehoshua Hanei Tanna'ei (הני תנאי) Hanei Tanna'ei Be'mashkeh Omad Le'ibud Pligi
(במשקה עומד לאיבוד פליגי). Be'mashkeh Omad Le'ibud Pligi You're right, that debate
about squeezing the olives to see how ripe they are is a
debate when it is a liquid, you want it, and it's just
going to waste. V'hanach Tanna'ei (והנך תנאי), V'hanach Tanna'ei but the issue
about the bread is a different story: Be'mashkeh Omad Letzahtzecho Kamipligi (במשקה
עומד לצחצחו קמיפלגי). Be'mashkeh Omad Letzahtzecho Kamipligi It's not going Le'ibud (לאיבוד),
Le'ibud it's not totally being spilled on the floor, you're doing it
there to shine to give a shine
to the... Now again, it doesn't make so much sense why that
should be so bad. I mean, you're adding it, you want it
and so on. Again, what it would seem to make more sense
is that
well, whatever. Anyway, so that's an alternative read to the issue that
it's a question about משקה mashke that's coming to אוכל. ochel. Here
it's trying to claim that it would be a משקה, mashke, but
it's special because it's coming only to give a shine to it
and maybe that's close to הולך לאיבוד. holech le-ibud. Again, hard to
understand that. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara now continues. Okay, so we do
have those positions that if it's holech that משקה mashke that is
going to אוכל ochel is אוכל, ochel, although the גמרא Gemara tried
to say maybe it is a matter of debate. להלכה le-halacha we
actually do say that. So we say you can squeeze your lemon
on your fish, you can squeeze it on your salad, it doesn't
even have to be absorbed into the food, it just has to
be there to add taste to the food. And the but what
we don't do is what the גמרא Gemara possibly sounded like, which
is to squeeze it into a pot if eventually you're going to
put it in food. It has to at least directly go on
food as you're squeezing it, that is what we do say. But
that's and that actually is the הלכה. halacha. Not into liquids, that
would be a liquid, so that's not squeezing your lemon into tea.
והנך תנאי במשקה עומד. ve-hanach tanna'ei be-mashke amad. I'm sorry. אמר רבי
זירא אמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב, amar Rabbi Zeira amar
Rabbi Chiya bar Ashi amar Rav, סוחט אדם אשכול של ענבים לתוך
הקדרה ולא לתוך הקערה. soghed adam eshkol shel anavim le-toch hagedera ve-lo
le-toch keara. So exactly what we just said, even if you're dealing
with grapes, even though it could be a biblical concern, you could
squeeze it into the pot, maybe because it's headed to food or
certainly at least because there is already food in the pot, but
you cannot do it into a plate, into a dish, because that
is considered that it's existing as liquid and therefore that is obviously
what is forbidden. ודע, ve-da, now we move on from squeezing from
squeezing fruit to squeezing and their natural juices, to squeezing other
things and squeezing them out sometimes of juices they absorbed from the
outside. ודג לצירה, ve-dag le-tzirei, squeezing out a fish from its brine,
אפילו לתוך קערה, afilu le-toch keara, that you can do even into
a plate. Why is that? So it could be because there it's
clear that nobody wants to use fish brine and therefore you essentially
have no interest in it, and it doesn't have a name of
a שם משקה. shem mashke.
So that would be the simplest explanation. Another explanation could be even
if you do want it, רש"י Rashi a little bit indicates that
somehow fish brine might always have a status of אוכל ochel and
not משקה, mashke, not exactly clear why. But anyway the simpler explanation
is that there clearly you're doing it because you really are completely
uninterested in what comes out. יתיב רב דימי וקאמר להאי שמעתא. yasiv
Rav Dimi ve-kamar le-hai shmaita. רב דימי Rav Dimi was sitting and
saying over this discussion. אמר ליה אביי לרב דימי, amar lei Abaye
le-Rav Dimi, so אביי Abaye said to רב דימי, Rav Dimi, אתון
משמיה דרב מתניתו. ashu mi-shmei de-Rav masitan. You taught that idea of
squeezing out the fish
for to get the brine out in the name of רב Rav
and therefore ולא קשיא לכו, ve-lo kasha lechu, you didn't have any
problem. אנן, anan, we however, משמיה דשמואל מתנינן לה, mi-shmei de-Shmuel masninan
lah, we have that tradition in the name of שמואל. Shmuel. וקשיא
לן, ve-kasha lan, and we have a problem because שמואל, Shmuel, if
we have שמואל Shmuel saying that you can squeeze out a fish
to get the brine out, that seems to contradict something else that
שמואל Shmuel said. מי אמר שמואל דג לצירה אפילו לתוך קערה? mi
amar Shmuel dag le-tzirei afilu le-toch keara? Did שמואל Shmuel really say
a fish for its brine even into a plate? ואיתמר, ve-itmar, it
was taught,
כבשים שסחטן. kevashim she-sechtan. Now you squeezed out of vegetables that have
been pickled. Okay, now that type of a case, well let's take
a look, let's read what the opinions are and then we'll talk
what it's about. כבשים שסחטן. kevashim she-sechtan. אמר רב, amar Rav, לגופן
מותר. le-gufan muttar. If you're doing it just for the sake of
making the vegetables more edible, that's fine, that's not a סחיטה sechita
problem. By the way, not so clear why it's not a בורר
borer problem, but we won't get into that. But it's not a
סחיטה sechita problem because you're completely not interested in the juices that
come out.
למימיהן, le-meimeihen, if however you're interested that you want the vegetable juice
or the
pickled the pickled juice that's coming out, the well whatever, yeah it's
vegetables, I don't know if you call it brine, but anyway the
pickled juice that's coming out, then פטור אבל אסור. patur aval assur.
You're exempt but it's forbidden. Now why are you exempt? Interesting point,
two ways to explain why you're exempt here. רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafot each take a different way. One is that anything that's not
with that's not wine or olive oil you're exempt. So assuming that
the brine here is some type of vinegar and so on and
it's not from grapes and it's not from olives, so then fine
then because what comes out is not a liquid that you're חייב
chayav for for squeezing, it's not a formal שם משקה. shem mashke.
That's one explanation. רש"י Rashi actually says that you are pickling them
in- רש"י Rashi says יין וחומץ, yayin ve-chometz, right. So רש"י Rashi
says no we could even be talking that they do have wine
absorbed in them. So why are you exempt? Because they do not
naturally grow in the object. Something that absorbs from the outside is
not a concern of סחיטה. sechita. Now תוספות Tosafot says really? תוספות
Tosafot says what about why is there such a problem of tightening
like the the cloth at the opening of the barrel because you'll
squeeze out and all these things about mopping up wine and all
this stuff if it's from the outside. If it's something absorbed from
the outside is not a biblical סחיטה, sechita, why do we make
a גזירה? gezeira? He says, alright fine, it's only rabbinic but we're
still making the גזירה. gezeira. We do sometimes make גזירה gezeira on
rabbinic but this becomes a very important discussion about what are the
parameters for the biblical סחיטה. sechita. Number one is wine and oil.
Number two is here there seems like you're פטור אבל אסור patur
aval assur either because it's not wine and oil or because it's
not naturally growing within which would be fascinating because then all the
cases of wiping up spills and squeezing out or whatever would all
be rabbinic, at least according to this.
Wait, don't we disagree with all those other ones that we had
before then? That what? Meaning all those ones were rabbinic but this
isn't even a problem rabbinically?
No, פטור אבל אסור. patur aval assur. Oh okay, פטור אבל אסור.
patur aval assur. Okay, but we'll talk about so anyway we'll more
about that in a minute but that's stage number one.
Okay, where were we?
ושלקות, Vishlokos, now how about things that are not brine vegetables but
boiled
vegetables, בין לגופן בין למימיהן מותר. bein leguphan bein lememeihen mutar. Even
if you do it together because you want the water, it's permissible.
Why? So according to רש״י Rashi presumably that's because the water there
is not olive oil or vinegar. So and it's just water. I
mean it's funny if you said anything would have a שם משקה
shem mashke it would be water, but anyway it's not even something
that maybe is ever like a natural—I'm sorry, תוספות Tosfos would say
it's not wine or olive oil. רש״י Rashi would say it's presumably
it's both. A, it's from the outside and it's not that. So
okay, so therefore it's totally מותר. mutar. So why is it—so let
me just—I did that a little quickly—why is it totally מותר? mutar?
Why is it different if it's brine as opposed to if it's
water? So you could say either the reason that if it's that
in this case it's not olive oil or wine it's pure water,
so therefore it's less of a משקה, mashke, it's less similar to
the classic case of squeezing out fruit juices because here it's just
water that's coming out so it's completely unlike the classic case. Or
you could try to argue that even if it's למימיהן lememeihen somehow
that type of a liquid has no significance, which is similar to
the issue of the fish brine. So anyway those are the two
stages about whether you're doing it for actual like the pickle juice
which has more significance which is rabbinically a problem or whether you're
doing it for the water which has no significance and therefore is
not even rabbinically a problem. That's
רב. Rav. Now ושמואל אמר, v'Shmuel amar, now שמואל Shmuel does not
make this distinction so it's easier to understand שמואל. Shmuel. אחד כבשים
ואחד שלקות, Echad kevashim ve-echad shelachot,
whether it is pickled vegetables or boiled
vegetables, לגופן מותר, leguphan mutar, if it's just to make the vegetables
more edible it's fine, you're not interested in the liquid. למימיהן פטור
אבל אסור. Lememeihen patur aval assur. But for the water, that's considered
to be—not you're not חייב, chayav, but it is rabbinically forbidden. So
he says look, if you want the juices that come out, whatever
the case is, brine, water, whatever those juices are, it's enough similar
to squeezing vegetables that squeezing fruit that if you want the juices
to come out it's going to be rabbinically forbidden. So now we've
got a problem because we said you could squeeze the fish for
its brine even if you want the water. That idea that sometimes
you could want the the juice that comes out and it would
still be permissible, the only one who has said that is רב.
Rav. רב Rav says if you squeeze boiled vegetables for their water,
sometimes the liquid that comes out is so insignificant that it is
even permissible to do it for the sake of the liquid that
comes out. But שמואל Shmuel doesn't say that. שמואל Shmuel says even
boiled vegetables for their water as long as you want the liquid
it's at least rabbinically forbidden. So how could שמואל Shmuel teach? So
we have a tradition that שמואל Shmuel said you could squeeze the
fish out for its brine, why is that any different than forbidding
squeezing boiled vegetables out for their water? So we have
this problem. So אמר ליה, amar leh, so that was what אביי
Abaye said back to רב דימי. Rav Dimi. רב דימי Rav Dimi
taught in the name of רב. Rav. אביי Abaye had in the
name of שמואל. Shmuel. So רב דימי Rav Dimi said back to
אביי, Abaye, האלהים, ha-Elohim, by God, עיני ראו ולא זר, einai ra-u
velo zar, my own eyes have seen and not somebody else, which
is quoting a פסוק pasuk in איוב. Iyov. מפומי דרבי ירמיה שמיע
לי, Mipumei de-Rabbi Yirmiya shemiah li, I heard this tradition from רבי
ירמיה, Rabbi Yirmiya, ורבי ירמיה מרבי זעירא ורבי זעירא מרב חייא בר
אשי ורב חייא בר אשי מרב. v'Rabbi Yirmiya mi-Rabbi Zeira v'Rabbi Zeira
mi-Rav Chiya bar Ashi v'Rav Chiya bar Ashi mi-Rav. It's just not
somebody quoting רב. Rav. I am part of the exact
tradition. I know I heard עד מפי עד מפי עד, ed mi-pi
ed mi-pi ed, I know that this is from רב Rav so
you don't have to worry about it. You've got a contradiction—שמואל Shmuel
contradicts himself, trust me, this is from רב, Rav, solves your problem.
It's quite interesting though, I myself have seen it when he actually
had still five generations removed. What do you mean he didn't just
hear it in his name, I actually am part of the chain
of tradition. Okay. Like A says X, B
says Y, C says Z. Right, same thing
right?
That—you mean how is this different than any other type of a
case where he's saying it? Yeah, well maybe that's the—let me see.
אמר רב זעירא, Amar Rav Zeira, yeah you're right, it's that normal
אמר רב זעירא אמר רב חייא בר
אשי רב,
amar Rav Zeira amar Rav
Chiya bar Ashi Rav, right.
Yeah. Sometimes it's just known that so you know that like I
didn't hear it from a particular אמורא. Amora. Right. But but if
I say I heard it from A who heard it from B
who heard it from C, it's the same as he's saying.
Right I know I mean that and that's how the גמרא Gemara
began it, אמר רב זעירא אמר רב חייא בר אשי
אמר רב,
amar Rav Zeira amar Rav Chiya bar Ashi
amar
Rav, so maybe the person who questioned him didn't know
that. Well, it is interesting. No, no, no.
Here actually is interesting because it starts with אמר רבי זירא אמר
רבי חייא בר אשי Amar Rabbi Zeira Amar Rabbi Chiya Bar Ashi
and when he gives you the chain of tradition he says I
heard it from רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeya and רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeya
from רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. So when he first repeated it he
didn't it was not clear you know he might you know that
you know he wasn't necessarily part of the direct chain of tradition
because he had skipped a step and now he's filling in the
step to show how really he got it from the people that
had directly heard it. But it's a good point. Okay. That okay
גופא. Gufa. Now let's get back to that statement. כבשים שסחטן Kvashim
she'sachtan אמר רב Amar Rav לגופן מותר legufan mutar למימיהן פטור אבל
אסור lemeimeihen patur aval assur if you're doing it for the for
the to make it more edible that's fine. If you're doing it
to get out the liquids it's exempt either as we said because
it's absorbed from the outside or because it's not wine or oil.
ושלוקות בין לגופן בין למימיהן מותר Ushlukot bein legufan bein lemeimeihen mutar
but boiled vegetables even if you want the liquid is permissible again
not exactly clear why but for some reason we'll say that it's
either completely not similar to the biblical case of squeezing grapes and
olives or because the liquid is considered so much like waste that
even if you want it it doesn't have a שם משקה shem
mashkeh it's completely insignificant. ושמואל אמר Ushmuel amar anyway Rav allows it
sometimes even למימיהן lemeimeihen it could be מותר. mutar. And Shmuel said
אחד זה ואחד זה echad zeh ve'echad zeh in either case לגופן
מותר legufan mutar for their for the sake of making the vegetables
more edible that's fine למימיהן פטור אבל אסור lemeimeihen patur aval assur
but if you whenever you want the liquids it's at least rabbinically
forbidden. Okay regardless so whether it's fish brine or water from boiled
vegetables whenever you want the liquids it's rabbinically forbidden. רבי יוחנן אמר
Rabbi Yochanan amar now Rabbi Yochanan says אחד כבשים ואחד שלוקות echad
kvashim ve'echad shlukot whether you're dealing with pickled or boiled vegetables לגופן
מותר legufan mutar I agree that if you're doing it to make
it more edible it's fine because it's not מפרק mifarek it's not
you know it's not the classic case of squeezing because you don't
want the liquid. But למימיהן lemeimeihen if you want the liquid חייב
חטאת chayav chatas you're חייב חטאת. chayav chatas. So here you actually
have like you know extremes from מותר mutar at least in the
case of boiled vegetables to פטור patur which is Shmuel to Rabbi
Yochanan which is חייב חטאת. chayav chatas. Anytime you want the liquids
it doesn't matter that they're coming from the outside doesn't matter that
they're not wine or olive oil anytime you squeeze something to get
out the liquid חייב חטאת. chayav chatas.
Okay מיתיבי Meisivei but doesn't the גמרא Gemara always not like that
how can you get from
I know but the well it did ask it once before but
anyway here but it's not no it's not always bothered with it.
Even the answer given before when it said how could you have
such extremes was well as long as you're mentioning the stages along
the way the spectrum it's not was not bothered by that. מיתיבי
Meisivei I'll ask you on this סוחטין כבשים בשבת לצורך השבת sochtin
kvashim beShabbos letzorach haShabbos we have a ברייתא braisa you can squeeze
pickled vegetables on שבת Shabbos if you're going to eat them on
שבת Shabbos אבל לא למוצאי שבת aval lo leMotzaei Shabbos not for
Friday not for Saturday night that's like you know הכנה. hachana. וזיתים
וענבים Vezeisim va'anavim לא יסחוט lo yischot but don't be don't let
me catch you squeezing olives or or grapes ואם סחט חייב חטאת
ve'im sachat chayav chatas and there you're חייב חטאת. chayav chatas. Okay
now קשיא לרב קשיא לשמואל קשיא לרבי יוחנן. kashya leRav kashya liShmuel
kashya leRabbi Yochanan. On the face of it this is difficult to
everyone because this sounds like the only first of all let's start
with Rabbi Yochanan it sounds like the only thing you're חייב חטאת
chayav chatas is on grapes and olives whereas Rabbi Yochanan will have
you חייב חטאת chayav chatas in pretty much anything. Number two where
it says
that the other stuff you can do it it doesn't distinguish למימיהן
lemeimeihen לגופן legufan and so on and everybody else you know at
least made some distinction along those lines. So basically everybody will read
their own position into this רב מתרץ לטעמיה שמואל מתרץ לטעמיה רבי
יוחנן מתרץ לטעמיה. Rav metaretz leta'amei Shmuel metaretz leta'amei Rabbi Yochanan metaretz
leta'amei. Okay everybody explains it according to how it fits their position.
רב מתרץ לטעמיה Rav metaretz leta'amei here's how Rav would read it.
סוחטין כבשים בשבת לצורך השבת אבל לא למוצאי שבת sochtin kvashim beShabbos
letzorach haShabbos aval lo leMotzaei Shabbos you can squeeze out pickled vegetables
for שבת Shabbos במה דברים אמורים bameh devarim amurim לגופן legufan that's
if you want to actually eat the vegetables themselves then even then
it's fine with לצורך השבת letzorach haShabbos אבל לא למוצאי שבת aval
lo leMotzaei Shabbos I'm sorry במה דברים אמורים bameh devarim amurim לגופן
legufan אבל למימיהן aval lemeimeihen but if you want the juices the
pickles the pickling you know the pickling juice פטור אבל אסור patur
aval assur that's rabbinically forbidden because that at least has some significance.
ושלוקות Ushlukot however boiled
vegetables those בין לגופן בין למימיהן מותר bein legufan bein lemeimeihen mutar
that would be completely permissible. Okay now by the way Rav has
not read so much into this ברייתא. braisa. The ברייתא braisa didn't
talk about שלוקות. shlukot. To say שלוקות shlukot are totally permissible is
fine. All he's really done is qualified that the case of כבשים
kvashim of pickled vegetables is talking when it is לגופן legufan as
opposed to למימיהן. lemeimeihen. וזיתים וענבים Vezeisim va'anavim now olives and grapes
לא יסחוט lo yischot don't squeeze them ואם סחט חייב חטאת ve'im
sachat chayav chatas and if you squeeze them you're חייב חטאת chayav
chatas presumably you did it למימיהן lemeimeihen right but it's interesting that
it doesn't distinguish but presumably you did it למימיהן lemeimeihen because we
had the whole discussion before that if it's coming into אוכל ochel
and so on it's not automatically חייב. chayav. Okay that's anyway how
Rav explains. So Rav really has it the easiest. כבשים kvashim you
can do if it's לגופן legufan וזיתים וענבים vezeisim va'anavim you're חייב
חטאת chayav chatas if it's למימיהן lemeimeihen let's say. Although again the
גמרא Gemara doesn't I'm sticking in the words למימיהן. lemeimeihen. שמואל מתרץ
לטעמיה Shmuel metaretz leta'amei Shmuel explains according to his reasoning. סוחטין כבשים
בשבת לצורך השבת sochtin kvashim beShabbos letzorach haShabbos you can squeeze out
pickled vegetables והוא הדין לשלוקות vehu hadin leshlukot really also boiled vegetables
like it's a bigger חידוש chiddush to say pickled vegetables. Pickled vegetables
are According to רב Rav were more problematic. But both pickled and
boiled vegetables are allowed. So what does שמואל Shmuel do? He adds
the word boiled vegetables to the pickled, says the it's really no
distinction, which is not a big point. במה דברים אמורים, B'meh devarim
amurim, לגופא. legufa. Now when is it allowed? If you're trying to
eat the make the you know make the the food more edible.
אבל למימיהם, aval l'mimeihem, but if you want to get out the
liquid, פטור אבל אסור, pattur aval assur, that's rabbinically forbidden even in
the case of pickled even in boiled vegetables. אבל זיתים וענבים, aval
zeitim v'anavim, now olives and grapes, לא יסחוט ואם סחט חייב חטאת,
lo yischot v'im sachat chayav chatat, that you could be חייב חטאת
chayav chatat for. So all שמואל Shmuel did was very similar to
רב, Rav, he said the first case where it said מותר muttar
was
לגופן legufan and when it's saying כבשים kvashim it's really שלקות shlakos
has the exact same הלכה. halacha. Neither of those were too forced.
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is going to have the hardest time because
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan has חייב חטאת chayav chatat before you get
to olives and grapes. רבי יוחנן מתרץ לטעמיה, Rabbi Yochanan metaretz l'ta'ameih,
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan explains to his reasoning, סוחט כבשים לצורך השבת
אבל לא למוצאי שבת אחד כבשים ואחד שלקות. socheit kvashim l'tzorech ha'Shabbos
aval lo l'motzaei Shabbos echad kvashim v'echad shlakos. You can squeeze things,
it doesn't matter if it's pickled or boiled. במה דברים אמורים, B'meh
devarim amurim, under what
circumstances? לגופא. legufa. אבל למימיהם לא יסחוט. aval l'mimeihem lo yischot. All
of this is when you're doing it to eat the vegetable. But
if you're doing it for the liquid, you cannot and ואם סחט,
v'im sachat, if you did squeeze anything for their liquids, נעשה כמי
שסחט זיתים וענבים וחייב חטאת. na'aseh k'mi shesachat zeitim v'anavim v'chayav chatat.
It's as bad as if you squeezed olives and grapes וחייב חטאת.
v'chayav chatat. That's the biggest squeeze. That's the biggest forced explanation because
it says you're חייב chayav for olives and grapes and what he
says is it means anything that is למימיהן l'mimeihen is as if
it's olives and grapes, okay? The ברייתא Baraisa is most misleading according
to רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Now let's just see where this ends
up. אמר רב חייא בר אשי אמר רב, Amar Rav Chiya bar
Ashi amar Rav, דבר תורה אינו חייב אלא על דריסת זיתים וענבים
ובלבד. devar Torah eino chayav ela al drisas zeitim v'anavim u'bilvad. Biblically
you're not חייב chayav unless you're actually squeezing olives and grapes. וכן
תנא דבי מנשה, v'chein tana d'bei Menashe, and so they taught in
the house of Menashe, דבר תורה אינו חייב אלא על דריסת זיתים
וענבים ובלבד, devar Torah eino chayav ela al drisas zeitim v'anavim u'bilvad,
only on olives and grapes. Now before we get onto the next
part, I'll say a word about the הלכה. halacha. Okay, first of
all, it says דריסה, drisa, stomping on. You know, maybe even using
your hands is a שינוי, shinuy, who knows? But certainly just olives
and grapes and the categorical way it says it, and this is
what I was telling you the other day, it sounds like even
if you got something that was completely דרך, derech, a Valencia orange
which is grown for squeezing, it doesn't matter. Only something that produces
olive oil or wine, that is a classic משקה, mashkeh, that's the
only thing that is biblical. Now how about, that's how about these
other types of scenarios about like למימיהן, l'mimeihen, what's אסור, assur, what's
מותר? muttar? So if you take a look at תוספות, Tosfos, he
quotes רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel which is not how we rule. רבי
יוחנן אמר אחד כבשים ושלוקות, Rabbi Yochanan amar echad kvashim v'shlukos,
I'm just skipping to like the רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan five lines
down, one, two, three, six lines under the words רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan he says ופירש ר''ח, u'peireish R''Ch, Rabbeinu Chananel explains, דהלכה כרבי
יוחנן. d'halacha k'Rabbi Yochanan. We rule like רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. Oh
wow. דקיימא לן כוותיה לגבי רב ושמואל. d'kaima lan kevaseih l'gabbei Rav
u'Shmuel. Okay, so which means that you can never do it למימיהן,
l'mimeihen, fine, שמואל Shmuel said that too. But it also means that
if you do it למימיהן, l'mimeihen, חייב חטאת, chayav chatat, against what
we just read. Okay, ואשמעינן מילתא דרבי יוחנן דאסור לסחוט כבשים ושלוקות
למימיהם ואם סחט חייב חטאת. v'ashmeinan milta d'Rabbi Yochanan d'assur l'ischot kvashim
v'shlukos l'mimeihem v'im sachat chayav chatat. Okay, so actually it would all
be חייב חטאת. chayav chatat. And not only that, ולא הפריש בין
סחיטה בין לקדירה לקערה. v'lo hifrish bein s'chita bein l'kdeira l'ke'ara. It
wouldn't and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan doesn't distinguish between whether it's going
into food or into a plate. So according to
רבינו חננאל, Rabbeinu Chananel, unless you're doing it for the sake of
making the food edible, anytime you're doing it to extract the liquid,
whatever liquid it is, whether it's absorbed from the outside or whether
it naturally grew in, and even if it's going into food, חייב
חטאת. chayav chatat. Okay, we do not rule like רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, we rule like the simple sense one gets by the end
of the גמרא, Gemara, that only grapes and olives are דאורייתא. d'Oraisa.
If you do it into food, like we said yesterday, it's מותר,
muttar, although there people are חושש choshesh for רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel
to say don't do grapes and olives into food, okay, even though
because you know, that is a potential דאורייתא. d'Oraisa. But basically into
food is מותר, muttar, only grapes and olives are דאורייתא, d'Oraisa,
and all and these other types of things, if you're doing it
לגופא legufa it's מותר, muttar, the vegetable's מותר לכתחילה, muttar l'chatchila, and
if you're doing it למימיהן, l'mimeihen, then it's going to be פטור
אבל אסור pattur aval assur presumably like either רב Rav or שמואל,
Shmuel, presumably we'll go like we go like שמואל, Shmuel, I mean
it's whatever, but anyway that you know, even the cases of boiled
vegetables should at least rabbinically not be be no good. Now I
do want to say though that there is still some remaining debate
because it gets to the question about like squeezing out the towel,
you know, why the גמרא Gemara has so many issues with it,
why is that not consider you know, why is that considered might
be חייב chayav and this might and this would
be פטור. pattur. So it could be that the cases of squeezing
out were specifically cases where it absorbed wine, like our case גמרא
Gemara began, that you have a bottle a barrel of wine that
broke, or you have a plug in a barrel of wine. So
the concerns there could be that you are not only you know,
wanting the liquid that comes out, but you actually it actually is
wine and that gets that's a central concern. essentially תוספות Tosafot's approach.
Okay, but according to רש"י, Rashi, it would seem that all of
those cases are only going to be
rabbinic because they are coming from the outside. There's a third opinion
actually that says that's even more stress, and that says that when
something was a liquid first and then got absorbed, it retains the
status of a liquid.
And therefore when you squeeze it, you're חייב chayiv even if it's
not wine and olive oil, right? Because it had the status of
a liquid prior to this. So that's more along the lines of
what maybe רב יוחנן Reb Yochanan is talking about. Okay, right.
But anyway, but I did want to say that that is the
הלכה halacha that we basically assume
wine and olive oil is דאורייתא, deoraita, you can squeeze things into
food, that's okay, other types of vegetables,
pickled or boiled, squeeze it for גופה, gufah, not למימיהן. lemeimehen. If
you do squeeze it למימיהן lemeimehen and so on, then it becomes
the issue about like the towel that you're squeezing out and that
you want the juice out, could that ever be דאורייתא deoraita if
it absorbs from the outside? If it's absorbing olive oil or wine,
then there's more of a potential of it being דאורייתא. deoraita. Yes.
Was there a question?
Sorry. Yeah, basically just there's a very long רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel
there, does he qualify that at all or?
Not really, I mean תוספות Tosafot quotes more רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel
which we skipped. Okay. All right. So that is the הלכה למעשה
halacha lema'aseh of all of that, but again point out as I
said that the issues about why
squeezing clothes with water in them is such a problem is not
so clear given this and a number of ראשונים Rishonim really emphasize
that the problem of squeezing clothes is not like squeezing vegetables, it's
all about ליבון, libun, it's all about laundering, not about, right there
are cases למימיהן, lemeimehen, you absorb the wine and now you want
to squeeze it out. But most of those cases are not that.
Let's continue now in the גמרא. Gemorah. So the ברייתא Baraita will
pick up again from the last line in the גמרא. Gemorah. וכן
תנא דבי מנשה, Vechein tana debei Menashe, דבר תורה אינו חייב אלא
על סחיטת זיתים וענבים בלבד, devar Torah eino chayiv ella al schitas
zeisim v'anavim bilvad, ואין עד מפי עד
כשר אלא לעדות אשה בלבד. veein ed mipi ed kasher ella l'eidus
isha bilvad. Back to it, okay. It's just two things that don't,
you know, take this out of, this is only in this case.
So one is like a קולא, kula, limiting it, it's only דאורייתא
deoraita by olives and grapes, and the other's like a חומרא chumra
where sometimes we allow secondhand testimony, hearsay evidence, testimony, but that's only
when it's coming to allow a woman to get remarried. When there's
questions if her husband died, and then you have עד מפי עד,
ed mipi ed, hearsay, and you know somebody heard it from somebody
who heard it from somebody, as long as at the end of
the line somebody claims that they actually saw the husband die, so
it's not just a rumor, it's at least it's a report again
like we had before on the עמוד א', amud alef, right? But
some chain of some chain then we allow a woman to remarry,
that only applies to issues of a woman remarrying, no other cases
do we allow testimony of that nature. איבעיא להו, Ibaya lehu, so
then the question was
raised, this is grafted over from בכורות. Bechorot. עד מפי עד לעדות
בכור מהו? Ed mipi ed l'eidus bechor mahu? How about an עד
מפי עד ed mipi ed for the testimony of a בכור? bechor?
What's the issue?
כהנים Kohanim were suspect of making a blemish in the בכור bechor
that they would give. A ישראל Yisrael would give a בכור bechor
to the כהן, Kohen, an animal, the כהן Kohen would have to
bring it as a קרבן. korban. Pain in the neck to bring
it as a קרבן korban depending on where you live in particular.
So what they but if it had a blemish then you could
eat it outside the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash not as a קרבן,
korban, you don't have to redeem it, it's perfect. So the כהנים
Kohanim were suspect of putting blemishes which is a biblical prohibition in
the בכורות bechors they got. So if a כהן Kohen had a
blemish in his בכור bechor and it was not seen that when
the ישראל Yisrael gave it to him it had a blemish, but
he only discovered the blemish or the blemish came out after, there
wasn't evidence that it was before, then he is not allowed to
eat from that בכור bechor unless he can bring evidence that it
got the blemish in a normal way and he was not the
one that actually imposed, made the blemish. Okay.
So can you accept hearsay evidence to allow him to eat this
בכור bechor with the blemish? So רב אמי אסר, Rav Ami assar,
רב אמי Rav Ami says it's forbidden, so רב אסי שרי, Rav
Assi sharei, רב אסי Rav Assi says permissible. אמר ליה רב אמי
לרב אסי, Amar lei Rav Ami le-Rav Assi, so רב אמי Rav
Ami said והא תנא דבי מנשה אין עד מפי עד כשר אלא
לעדות אשה בלבד, ve-ha tana debei Menashe ein ed mipi ed kasher
ella l'eidus isha bilvad, we have a ברייתא Baraita that says the
only time hearsay works is to allow a woman to remarry, so
for this thing like בכור bechor no. So אימא, eima, so he
says no no, here's what it means: לעדות שהאשה כשירה לה בלבד,
l'eidus she-isha keshera lah bilvad, it doesn't mean testimony for the sake
of a woman to get her remarried, it means for the type
of testimony that we also believe women for. So anytime we believe
a woman in testimony, we would also believe hearsay evidence. So we
believe women in the category of letting a woman remarry,
if a woman saw her husband die,
women's testimony is allowed, so both women's testimony and hearsay evidence, and
by בכור bechor we know we believe women's testimony to testify that
this got the blemish later, so therefore we would also believe עד
מפי עד. ed mipi ed. So it's very creative rereading, but you
understand the logic, when we drop the Formal requirements of testimony and
then we should then the same way if we're going to allow
women we should allow עד מפי עד. eid mipi eid. If anything,
women is more, עד מפי עד eid mipi eid is less reliable.
It's hearsay. You didn't even see it directly. Women to be like
a formal exclusion. עד מפי עד eid mipi eid there's reasons to
exclude that testimony. So that's what he says. Whenever we allow women's
testimony, we allow hearsay, and therefore it applies to בכור bechor as
well.
רב יימר Rav Yemar allowed עד מפי עד eid mipi eid for
בכור bechor to allow a כהן Kohen to eat the בכור. bechor.
קרי ליה מרימר. Karei lei Maremar. So funny, רב אשי, Rav Ashi,
רב אבני, Rav Abni, רב יימר, Rav Yemar, מרימר. Maremar. Anyway, all
the names here are almost the same. קרי ליה מרימר, Karei lei
Maremar, so מרימר Maremar said about רב יימר, Rav Yemar, יימר שרי
בוכרא, Yemar sharei buchra, יימר Yemar the one who permits firstborns. But
he obviously was sort of trying to put him down. But והלכתא,
v'hilchisa, nevertheless, the הלכה halacha is עד מפי עד eid mipi eid
is כשר kosher for בכור. bechor. We actually do allow it for
בכור, bechor, which means that we allow עד מפי עד eid mipi
eid whenever we drop formal requirements of testimony, whenever we would allow
women. At least that's what it sounds like, which is a radical
reread of when we allow עד מפי עד. eid mipi eid. Last
case in the משנה Mishnah is if you basically mashed up some
cakes of honey, which is the way you get it out of
the hives, and then the liquid, the
honey sort of comes out. It started coming out before שבת Shabbat
and continues on שבת, Shabbat, then רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that
you can have the honey. It's not a problem, as it would
be by the grapes and the olives. So כי אתא רב הושעיא
מנהרדעא, ki ata Rav Hoshia miNarda, when רב הושעיא Rav Hoshia came
from
נהרדעא, Narda, אתא ואייתי מתניתא בידיה, ata v'aiti masnisa biyadei, he came
and he brought a
ברייתא. braisa. זיתים וענבים שרסקן מערב שבת, zeisim va'anavim she-riskan me'erev Shabbat,
if you have olives and grapes that
you pressed from before שבת, Shabbat, ויצאו מעצמן אסורין, v'yatzu me'atzman asurin,
and then the juices came out on their own on שבת, Shabbat,
maybe it started before שבת, Shabbat, it's forbidden. רבי אליעזר ורבי שמעון
מתירין, Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbi Shimon matirin, but רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon allow. So אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef,
so רב יוסף Rav Yosef says, וגבי יתר אתא לאשמועינן, v'gabbi yoser
atsu l'shmueinan, what did that add to our משנה? Mishnah? Our משנה
Mishnah also said רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer allowed. So what, one more
person, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? That's a
big deal to add רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi
Eliezer, big deal. So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, אביי Abaye
said back to him, טובא קא משמע לן, tuva kamashma lan, this
is a big חידוש. chiddush. It's not just רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
that he's adding. כלום קא משמע לן דאי מתניתין, klum kamashma lan
d'ee masnisin, what did our משנה Mishnah say, when did our משנה
Mishnah say רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer allows it? When you chopped up
honey. Okay, that's very different than chopping up grapes and olives. First
of all, as we've learned, grapes and olives is דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, so
there's more reason to make a גזירה. gezeira. But yet, so it's
a big חידוש. chiddush. דאי מתניתין הוה אמינא, d'ee masnisin hava amina,
I would have said, התם הוא דמעיקרא אוכלא ולסוף אוכלא. hasam hu
d'meikara ochla ul'sof ochla. Besides the issue that I just said about
grapes and olives, he says, look, by honey, before it started dissolving
and now that it's dissolved, it's not really like food and liquid.
Before it was food and even when it's honey, it's food. So
it's not even really...
the honeycombs are food?
No, no, no, but it means it was in the cake.
It means that it's not really changing. It's not really producing a
liquid. Even honey is a type of food, okay? So therefore that's
why maybe in the משנה Mishnah they say it's not a problem.
אבל הכא דמעיקרא אוכלא ולסוף משקה, aval hacha d'meikara ochla ul'sof mashke,
here it starts as food and then what comes out is משקה,
mashke, and I'll throw in it's also a biblical concern, olives and
grapes, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe even if it didn't start, maybe
even if it started before שבת, Shabbat, you couldn't according to them.
קא משמע לן kamashma lan that you can. Now this seems pretty
radical to apply it to olives and grapes. And it's only the
position of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, so
you would think we would reject it. But actually the שלחן ערוך
Shulchan Aruch פוסק paskens this way. Now what's the logic for it?
Why don't we say that if the juices are coming out, you'll
come to, who cares when they started coming out? Though they started
coming out before שבת, Shabbat, so what? You'll come to squeeze it,
you'll take the juices, you'll come to squeeze it, same concern about
being transgressing biblically. So the explanation is, and you might remember going
way back to the ביצה, Beitza, like first פרק, perek, בית הלל,
Beit Hillel, בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, about that even בית שמאי Beit
Shammai who says that you can't start מלאכות melachas from before שבת,
Shabbat, and have them go on שבת, Shabbat, says when you put
the beam on the olives and the juices already start coming out,
then you can leave it. Why? Because once the juice has started
coming out, then even if you were to continue squeezing it, it
would not be biblical. It's as if the juice has already come
out. So that is based on that, that presumably is the explanation
of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, and we
actually rule that way, that if the juices have started coming out
from before שבת, Shabbat, it actually is allowed to benefit from the
juices. What?
זיתים וענבים. zeisim va'anavim.
It means anything else too?
Possibly, although it depends, I think, maybe on some of the physical
properties of how much does the rest come out naturally once the
process starts. Okay, so now the משנה, Mishnah, now moving on. So
that was a whole big discussion about סחיטה. s'chita. Now we go
on to a completely different discussion. כל שבא בחמין מערב שבת, kol
she-ba b'chamin me'erev Shabbat, anything that was submerged in hot water from
before
שבת, Shabbat, שורין אותו בחמין בשבת, shorin oso b'chamin b'Shabbat, you can
submerge it in hot water on שבת. Shabbat. This is basically the
principle, it's very funny, because this should have been a discussion way
back when we did בישול. bishul. And the discussion we're going to
see in the גמרא Gemara is almost completely oblivious to all the
issues that were raised when we did בישול. bishul. You know, it's
a very, it's again, it's a very funny משנה Mishnah and a
funny גמרא. Gemara. But anyway, presumably the principle at play here is
אין בישול אחר בישול. ein Bishul achar Bishul. If you cooked it
before שבת, Shabbos, there's no problem resubmerging it into hot water on
שבת Shabbos because
of
אין בישול אחר בישול. ein Bishul achar Bishul. וכל שלא בא בחמין
מערב שבת, vechol shelo ba bachamin me'erev Shabbos, anything that did not,
was not already heated up in hot water from before שבת, Shabbos,
מדיחין אותו בחמין בשבת, madichin oso bachamin beShabbos, you can rinse it
with hot water,
okay, but you cannot actually submerge it in hot water. Now, rinsing
it in hot water, the question you want to ask is what?
Something is not cooked and I can rinse it in hot water.
Why isn't that a בישול Bishul concern, right? So maybe what it's
telling me is עירוי כלי ראשון, iruy kli rishon, when I pour
from a כלי ראשון kli rishon as opposed to submerging it in
the כלי ראשון, kli rishon, maybe that's not בישול. Bishul. Okay, that
is one way of reading this גמרא. Gemara. Some want to say
it's talking about עירוי כלי שני. iruy kli sheini. Again, it's funny
that this discussion, you know, never comes up in the earlier discussion
of really figuring out the parameters of בישול, Bishul, but here it
says you have something uncooked, you can pour hot water on it
on שבת. Shabbos. If we assume the hot water is יד סולדת
בו, yad soledes bo, maybe you want to claim it's not יד
סולדת בו, yad soledes bo, but if we assume it is יד
סולדת בו, yad soledes bo, then presumably it's saying that עירוי iruy
of a כלי ראשון kli rishon is not a problem. Because if
you remember, that was not clear from the גמרא. Gemara. גמרא Gemara
said כלי ראשון kli rishon is a problem, כלי שני kli sheini
is not a problem. We're מחמיר machmir even by כלי שני, kli
sheini, but within the גמרא, Gemara, כלי ראשון kli rishon is a
problem, כלי שני kli sheini is not a problem. Well, what about
pouring from a כלי ראשון? kli rishon? That's in the space between
כלי ראשון kli rishon and כלי שני. kli sheini. So that might
be what this משנה Mishnah is saying. Even if it's raw, you
can pour hot water on it on שבת, Shabbos, חוץ מן המליח
הישן chutz min hamaliach hayashan except for old salted fish, וקולייס האיספנין
vekulayas ha'ispanin and this other type of salted fish, שהדחתן זו היא
גמר מלאכתן, shedichasan zu hi gmar melachtan, that when you rinse those
in hot water, they've been salted, but when you rinse them in
hot water then that finishes the process, then they're really edible and
therefore it changes it, it makes it fully edible, so that is
forbidden. Now, does it biblical or rabbinic? We'll see in the גמרא.
Gemara.
Well, that's the issue. רש"י Rashi says, you have to look at
the last two words of רש"י Rashi on the משנה, Mishnah, he
says שזו גמר מלאכתן והוי בישול. shezo gmar melachtan vehavei Bishul. Okay,
now there actually is a question whether there's such a thing as
מכה בפטיש makeh b'patish by אוכלים. ochlim. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi has מכה
בפטיש makeh b'patish by אוכלים. ochlim. It actually talks about doing the
whole process of preparing food and says when you're done, you know,
then you're חייב chayav for a גמר מלאכה gmar melacha for מכה
בפטיש. makeh b'patish. The בבלי Bavli never explicitly says it, although this
משנה Mishnah sounds like it, and overwhelmingly the almost overwhelming consensus is
that there's no מכה בפטיש makeh b'patish by food. If there were,
you'd have a lot of interesting questions like why is בישול חמה
מותר? Bishul chama mutar? Why can you cook things in the sun?
Why isn't it a מכה בפטיש? makeh b'patish? You know, but anyway,
so therefore this גמר מלאכתן gmar melachtan is translated as בישול, Bishul,
not as מכה בפטיש. makeh b'patish. But the language does sound, Dov
is correct, does sound like מכה בפטיש. makeh b'patish.
You said it's because it makes it edible. As opposed to, let's
say, broccoli and you just cooked it more, right?
We'll talk about it. Right, the real thing is is that if
this was salted, the first case it's permissible because, you know, let's
wait, I'll get to the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. כגון מאי? kegon mai?
What's the case where if something has been submerged in hot water,
you know, already cooked, you can cook it again on שבת? Shabbos?
What would be an example of that? So אמר רב ספרא כגון
תרנגולתא דרבי אבא, amar Rav Safra kegon tarnigolta deRabbi Abba, like the
chicken of Rabbi Abba. ואמר רב ספרא, ve'amar Rav Safra, which was
apparently a way of producing chickens as we'll see, they really like
boiled it like, you know, extensively, almost to make it like mush.
Okay. ואמר רב ספרא זימנא חדא איקלע להתם, ve'amar Rav Safra zimna
chada ikla l'hasam, once I went there to, you know, Rabbi Abba,
ואכלי מיניה, ve'achli minei, and I ate from it, ואי לאו רבי
אבא דאשקיין חמרא בר תלתא טרפי, ve'ei lav Rabbi Abba d'ashkiyan chamra
bar tlata tarfei, and had Rabbi Abba not then given me wine
that was three years old, literally
three
leaves,
three years old, אסתסיי, istassai, I would have been, I would, you
know, I would have had to have like, רש"י Rashi says, forced
to regurgitate, it was so disgusting. Okay. Now רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
now we're going to talk about different people's feelings about foods from
other locales. So this chicken, this heavily boiled chicken, was an ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael food. Okay, so now, and here we're having רב
ספרא Rav Safra talking about how disgusting it was. So just to
be fair, we'll have רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan talking about what he
doesn't like about Babylonian cuisine. רבי יוחנן רייק מכותחא דבבלאי. Rabbi Yochanan
rayik mikutcha deBavla'ei. Rabbi Yochanan would spit, you know, would like gag
just thinking about Babylonian
כותח. Kusach. אמר רב יוסף ולרייק אנן מתרנגולתא דרבי אבא. amar Rav
Yosef velirayik anan mitarnigolta deRabbi Abba. Yeah, well we gag when we
think about the chicken of Rabbi Abba.
Okay. ועוד אמר רב גזא זימנא חדא, ve'od amar Rav Gaza zimna
chada, Rav Gaza at one time, איקלע להתם, ikla l'hasam, I went
over there to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, ועבדי כותחא דבבלאי, ve'avdi kutcha
deBavla'ei, and I made some Babylonian כותח, Kusach, which they're all saying
is disgusting, ושאילו מיניה כל בריחי מערבא, vesha'ilu minei kol briche'i Ma'arava,
and all the sick people of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael wanted a
sample of it. So they might think it's disgusting, but let me
tell... I tell you, when I was there, everybody wanted it, at
least all the sick people. It was a perfect remedy. So don't
make fun of our cuisine. Alright, we're going to revisit this theme
later in the דף. daf. כל שבא בחמין, Kol she'ba b'chamin, okay,
now anything that was not heated, anything raw you cannot submerge, but
you can pour hot water on it. Now, הדיח מאי? Hedich mai?
What happens if it now... okay, with the exception, so number one,
presumably putting it in hot water, let's say it's a כלי ראשון
kli rishon is בישול. bishul. Pouring hot water on it is let's
say עירוי כלי ראשון iruy kli rishon and not בישול. bishul. And
then it says, but if you've got these, if you've got these
fish and you do עירוי iruy and then they, even if you
pour hot water on it, those you can't pour hot water on.
Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, everything else you could pour hot water,
not these fish. So הדיח מאי, Hedich mai, what happens if you
do pour the hot water? אמר רב יוסף הדיח חייב חטאת. Amar
Rav Yosef hedich chayav chatas. Okay, this has very frequent if you
remember theme, the משנה Mishnah says don't do, don't do, don't do,
doesn't tell you as it דאורייתא, d'Oraisa, as it דרבנן, d'Rabanan, and
so on. The גמרא Gemara says what happens if you don't do
and basically there's always somebody that says it's still דאורייתא. d'Oraisa. חייב
חטאת. Chayav chatas. Sometimes there's pushback, here there isn't pushback. So what's
interesting about this is you're חייב חטאת. chayav chatas. Now for what?
You could have said not בישול, bishul, maybe if it's עירוי כלי
ראשון iruy kli rishon it's not בישול. bishul. So maybe it's גמר
מלאכה g'mar melacha that forces you to say that there's a concept
of גמר מלאכה g'mar melacha by food. The general explanation is it
is בישול, bishul, but then it opens up the idea of קלי
בישול. kallei bishul. That even though we generally have a rule that
things can't cook in a כלי שני, kli sheini, they can only
cook in a כלי ראשון, kli rishon, different types of foods that
cook more easily might have different parameters. And that seems to be
what the משנה Mishnah is saying. Most food you can pour boiling
hot... pour hot water on it, whether it's a כלי ראשון, kli
rishon, כלי שני, kli sheini, whatever, most foods it's okay. Here you
can't, and here if you do it, you're חייב חטאת, chayav chatas,
which means that some foods cook under different circumstances than other foods
and that it's not always a formal rule. Okay, and this is
important because this opens up the whole category of קלי בישול kallei
bishul that we generally don't put things even in a כלי שני
kli sheini when it's... when it's יד סולדת בו yad soledes bo
because we're always concerned it might be a type of food that
cooks more easily. Well, that concept is already in this משנה. Mishnah.
So
this משנה Mishnah without telling you what the operative principles
are often has in it a lot of very critical ideas. בישול
אחר בישול, Bishul achar bishul, אין בישול אחר בישול, ein bishul achar
bishul, עירוי iruy is okay, what is it, עירוי כלי ראשון, iruy
kli rishon, עירוי כלי שני, iruy kli sheini, and that some things
are קלי בישול kallei bishul like these fish and cook even in
different circumstances, it's not all formal rules, some things actually cook in
cases where other things would not. Okay. Now, אמר מר בריה דרבינא
אף אנן נמי תנינא, Amar Mar brei d'Ravina af anan nami tanina,
we taught similarly, חוץ ממליח הישן וקולייס האיספנין שהדחתן זו היא גמר
מלאכתן. chutz mi'maliach hayashan v'kolias ha'ispanin she'hadachtan zu hi g'mar melachtan. The
משנה Mishnah says there if you pour hot water on them, that's
the end of the process. So the language of גמר מלאכה g'mar
melacha sounds like it's a דאורייתא. d'Oraisa. שמע מינה, Shma mina, you
see that it really is a biblical problem. Of course, it sounds
like it's the דאורייתא d'Oraisa of מכה בפטיש, makeh b'patish, which is
not at least what רש"י Rashi says and what most פוסקים poskim
say. יתיב רבי חייא בר אבא ורבי אסי, Yasiv Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba v'Rabbi Assi,
now that we are... that's basically our halachic discussion. Now we're back
to cuisine. יתיב רבי חייא בר אבא ורבי אסי קמיה דרבי יוחנן.
Yasiv Rabbi Chiya bar Abba v'Rabbi Assi kamei d'Rabbi Yochanan. So Rabbi
Chiya bar Abba and Rabbi Assi were sitting in front of Rabbi
Yochanan. You'll remember Rabbi Yochanan was from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and
the one who would gag when he would think about the Babylonian
כותח. kutach. ויתיב רבי יוחנן וקא מנמנם. v'yasiv Rabbi Yochanan v'ka m'namnam.
Now Rabbi Yochanan was nodding off in sleep. אמר ליה רבי חייא
בר אבא לרבי אסי. Amar leh Rabbi Chiya bar Abba l'Rabbi Assi.
So what do the students do when the רבי Rebbe nods off?
They start schmoozing. So Rabbi Chiya bar Abba says to Rabbi Assi,
so he said, מפני מה עופות שבבבל שמנים? Mipnei mah ofos she'b'Bavel
sh'meinun? So they didn't have sports to talk about or the Academy
Awards. So here's what they thought about. He says,
why are the birds in בבל Bavel so fat, so much fatter
than those in ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? אמר ליה כלך למדבר עזה
ואראך שמנים מהם. Amar leh klach l'midbar Azza v'ar'echa sh'meinun mei'hem. You
know what, if you would go to the wilderness of עזה, Azza,
which is in
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, right? עזה, Azza, I'll even show you fatter
birds. So here basically the theme is going to be that Rabbi
Chiya bar Abba's going to be pointing out ways in which בבל
Bavel looks like it's better than ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, and Rabbi
Assi is going to defend the honor of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
and have an explanation for all of these phenomena.
Okay, מפני מה מועדים שבבבל שמחים? Mipnei mah moadim she'b'Bavel s'meichim? Why
are they so much more joyous in their holidays in בבל Bavel
than we seem to be here? מפני שאינן עניים. Mipnei she'einan aniyim.
So the answer is, you know what, they're so poor it's the
only day they have to rejoice. So he gets like an insult
in. So they're just so much more happier because they're so much
more depressed the rest of the year. Okay, מפני מה תלמידי חכמים
שבבבל מצוינין? Mipnei mah talmidei chachamim she'b'Bavel m'tzuyanin? Why do the תורה
Torah sages, the students in בבל, Bavel, why are they always dressed
so nicely? לפי שאינן בני תורה. Lefi she'einan bnei Torah. Because they
don't really have the goods, so they have to dress in a
way that people give them respect because of the way they dress
because they don't really have the goods. מפני מה עובדי כוכבים מזוהמין?
Mipnei mah ovdei kochavim m'zuhamin? Now it's not an ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael בבל Bavel issue. Why are non-Jews,
why do they have a smell? מפני שאוכלים שקצים ורמשים Mipnei she'ochlim
sh'katzim u'remashim because they eat trayf food and that gives their body
a bad body smell. Okay, so the last one is like not
which of these things is not like the other. Anyway, איתער בהו
רבי יוחנן. Is'ar behu Rabbi Yochanan. So Rabbi Yochanan woke up. אמר
להו. Amar lehu. So אמר להו, amar lehu, he said to them,
דרדקי, dardekei, kids, לא כך אמרתי לכם, lo kach amarti lachem, didn't
I tell you, אמור לחכמה אחותי את, emor lachochma achoti at, say
to wisdom you are my sister. אם ברור לך דבר כאחותך שאסורה
לך, im barur lecha davar ke'achotcha she'asura lach, if something is as
clear to you the same way it's clear that your sister is
forbidden to you, so אמרהו, omrehu, then you can say it. ואם
לאו לא תאמרהו, ve'im lav lo tomrehu, if not, not say it.
Now that's quite interesting because this is just שמועזי shmoozie and even
in שמועזינג shmoozing he's saying, you know, don't say things סתם stam
speculate. You should know things. It's also interest like חכמה, chochma, right?
It's not תורה, Torah, it's חכמה. chochma. Right, it's like, yeah, no,
but it's like worldly wisdom, it's not it's not תורה. Torah. But
even in worldly wisdom and even in שמועזינג, shmoozing, don't say things
unless you know what you're talking about. So אמרו ליה ולימא לן
מר, amru lei velima lan mar, so they said, so why don't
you so you explain to us, let the master explain to us
some of these phenomena. So let's go through them. מפני מה עופות
שבבבל שמנים, mipnei ma ofot she'be'Bavel shmenim, why are the birds in
בבל Bavel fat? Fatty? מפני שלא גלו, mipnei shelo galu, because the
birds never went into exile. The people also. Okay, and therefore they
were,
you know, they had the benefit of always being in the same
locale and that made them better, you know, improve improve their quality.
שנאמר, shene'emar, the verse says, by people not by bird, שאנן מואב
מנעוריו, shaanan Moav mine'urav, מואב Moav has been, you know, tranquil from
its very youth, ושקט הוא אל שמריו, veshokat hu el shmarav, it
rests on its lees like wine, you know, that it has never
been disturbed, it's on the lees of of the grapes. ובגולה לא
הלך, uvagola lo halach, it has never gone into exile. And the
end of the פסוק pasuk רש"י Rashi quotes is what's the end
of the פסוק? pasuk?
על כן עמד טעמו בו וריחו לא נמר.
al ken
amad tamo
bo vereicho lo namar.
There you go. So therefore it still has its taste and it
still has its smell. So the same way, so in ארץ בבל
Eretz Bavel nobody went into exile, things are good. ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, we went into exile, the birds went into exile, things aren't
as good. So by the way, the interesting thing about רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan is that as opposed to רבי אסי Rabbi Assi who's
always defending the honor of ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan is actually being willing to say no, actually there are ways
in which ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael does not have as good as
בבל. Bavel. Okay, so it's going to be quite interesting. Who says
birds go? I know. והכא מנלן דגלו, vehacha minalan degalu, and how
do we know that that they went into exile? דתניא detanya רבי
יהודה אומר נ"ב שנה לא עבר איש ביהודה. Rabbi Yehuda omer chamishim
u'shtayim shana lo avar ish bi'Yehuda.
For 40 for 52 years no person, not one man passed through
יהודה, Yehuda, so presumably if it's devoid of people,
it also has no animals, you know, that's an assumption. שנאמר, shene'emar,
על ההרים אשא בכי ונהי, al heharim esa vechi vanehi, ומעוף השמים
ועד
בהמה נדדו הלכו. u'me'of hashamayim ve'ad behema nadadu halachu. It does mention
animals, מעוף השמים ועד בהמה נדדו הלכו. me'of hashamayim ve'ad behema nadadu
halachu. From birds to animals. So actually, not only does he talk
about, he says איש, ish, but the real point is that the
פסוק pasuk says from birds to animals. So everything was exiled. הלכו.
halachu. So בהמה behema בגימטריא חמשין ותרתי be'gimatria chamshin v'tartei and בהמה
behema in גימטריא gimatria is 52. Now actually רש"י Rashi and תוספות
Tosafot say you don't really need the גימטריא gimatria because if you've
worked out the the dates they were in exile 52 until they
started coming back and they were rebuilding the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
then and at the end of 70 years then it was fully
rebuilt and so on. So the point though being that even the
animals went into גלות. galus. Now let's keep on going. אמר רבי
יעקב אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yaakov amar Rabbi Yochanan, כולם חזרו
חוץ מקוביא דאיספני. kulam chazru chutz mi'kuvaya d'Ispani. So
just to get a tie into our משנה, mishnah, all the birds
came back and all the animals and all the fish came back
except for this one variety of fish, the קוביא דאיספני. kuvaya d'Ispani.
Why did that not come back? דאמר רב, de'amar Rav, הני מדרי
דבבל מהדרי מיא לעין עיטם. hanei madrei de'Bavel mehadri maya l'Ein Eitam.
The inclines of בבל, Bavel, the waters of בבל Bavel all feed
into עין עיטם Ein Eitam which is the wellspring in ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael,
and that's how the fish from בבל Bavel can make their way
to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So if we have this fish in
בבל Bavel it should be in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. והאי, ve'hai,
but this one fish, כיון דלא שרי שדריה, keivan d'lo shari shidrei,
because its spine is not stiff, לא מצי סליק, lo matzi salik,
it cannot go up, you know, like it's like salmon that swim
upstream, so this this fish can't make the trip from בבל Bavel
up the hill to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. ולא מצי סליק. velo
matzi salik. Fine. So that's the end of the animals came back,
but they're not as good as in בבל. Bavel. מפני מה מועדים
שבבבל שמחים, mipnei ma moadim she'be'Bavel smeichim, why are the holidays in
בבל Bavel more joyful or so joyful? מפני שלא היתה בהם קללה,
mipnei shelo haita bahem klala, they never suffered the curse. דכתיב, dechtiv,
והשבתי כל משושה חגה חדשה ושבתה וכל מועדה. vehishbati kol mesosa chaga
chadsha ve'shabata vechol moada. Okay, so
God says I'm going to cause to cease all of the holidays
of, you know, in the גלות. galus. So therefore even though now
we've been returned, right, that curse, the remnants of that curse is
still with us and it's not as joyful. וכתיב, vechtiv, חדשיכם ומועדיכם
שנאה נפשי היו עלי לטרח. chodsheichem u'moadeichem sanea nafshi hayu alai latorach.
מאי היו עלי לטרח, mai hayu alai latorach, what's the burden? אמר
רבי אלעזר אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar Rabbi Elazar amar Hakadosh Baruch
Hu, לא דיי להם לישראל שחוטאין לפני, lo dai lahem l'Yisrael shechot'in
lefanai, it's not enough that they sin before me, אלא שמטריחים אותי
לידע איזה גזירה קשה אביא עליהם. ela shematrichim oti leida eizeh gzeira
kasha avi aleihem. I have to now figure out which bad edict
to bring upon them.
So
that was a burden even to punish them. Okay, as opposed to
fine. אמר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak, אין לך כל רגע ורגע
שלא בא בה בולשת לציפורי. ein lecha kol rega varega shelo ba
bah boleshet l'Tzipori.
There has not been one holiday that יום טוב Yom Tov where
a troops, king's troops have not come into ציפורי, Tzipori, not that
they were attacking it, but then you know they basically demand... and
people give them food and they quartered them and so on, right,
like one of the one of the Bill of Rights you don’t
have to quarter troops. Okay, well they had to do it then.
Okay, so there's on every יום טוב Yom Tov there's always something
going on. It's never fully joyous. ואמר רבי חנינא Va'amar Rabbi Chanina
אין לך כל רגע ורגע, ein lecha kol rega varega, there's not
one יום טוב Yom Tov in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael שלא בא
לטבריא אגמון וקמטון ובעל זמורא shelo ba l'Tiveria agmon vekamton uva'al zmora
that did not come to טבריא, Tiveria, you know, these are different
types of like governors and officers and so on, and therefore maybe
they know that we're all off from work and they think it's
a perfect time to press us into service. So in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael the ימים טובים Yamim Tovim are always afflicted, and this
is all from this קללה. klala. Now I do want to actually
say something interesting about this. First of all, it's certainly true as
a historical reality. In בבל Bavel the Jews had it much better
in terms of, you know, just the government was much more welcoming,
they had it financially much better. In ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they
lived under oppressive Roman
rule, the economics were harder. And by the way, this translates even
nowadays because ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
culture affected, you know, אשכנזי, Ashkenazi, בבל Bavel affected ספרדי, Sefardi, and
by the way a lot of those things remained true, remained true.
ספרדים Sefardim had it much more, were much more well accepted in
society, had it much more, were much more financially well off, אשכנזים
Ashkenazim much more oppressed, much harder time financially. And this issue of
שמחה simcha translates. There are at least two places where
differences אשכנזי Ashkenazi ספרדי Sefardi מנהגים. minhagim. אשכנזים Ashkenazim do not make
the ברכה bracha שהחיינו Shehecheyanu by a ברית bris and ספרדים Sefardim
do. Wow.
And אשכנזים, Ashkenazim, you know why we don't say ברכת כהנים Birkat
Kohanim every day? We're supposed to say it every day according to
the גמרא. Gemara. So the רמ"א Rama says because we don't have
any real שמחה simcha except on יום טוב Yom Tov and therefore
we don't say it, whereas ספרדים Sefardim say it every day. So
this idea that there's a שמחה simcha difference between בבל Bavel and
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael has played out in מנהגים minhagim even until
today between אשכנזים Ashkenazim and ספרדים. Sefardim. Yes.
And Spanish and Portuguese נוסח nusach from the Netherlands and the communities
that follow that do not recite ברכת כהנים Birkat Kohanim every day.
Ah, because they went to אשכנז. Ashkenaz.
They went to אשכנז Ashkenaz and were influenced. Very interesting point. Okay,
so let's wrap this up.
Okay, so now מפני מה תלמידי חכמים שבבבל מצויינים? Mipnei ma talmidei
chachamim shebeVavel metzuyanim? Why the Torah sages, why are they so, you
know, so nicely dressed? Why are they distinctive? So remember the answer
before was because they didn't have the goods. Here the answer is
לפי שאינם בני מקומא, lefi she'einam bnei mekoma, because they're not, they're
not locals. You know, they're imports, you know, they're
exiles. דאמרי אינשי, D'amri inshi, people say במתא שמאי, bemata shmai, in
your own city your name can carry, you know,
will garner honor. בלא מתא, Belo mata, if it's not your city
and nobody recognizes you תותבאי, totvai, then you have to dress so
that you are distinctive so that you get the honor that you
deserve. So it's because of גלות, galut, because they were exiled, that's
why. But again, nothing bad, nothing good, that's just a reality. הבאים
ישרש יעקב יציץ ופרח ישראל, Haba'im yashresh Yaakov yatzitz ufarach Yisrael, so
those that are come, you know, will set root and will flower
forth Israel when they return. תני רב יוסף Tani Rav Yosef אלו
תלמידי חכמים שבבבל. elu talmidei chachamim shebeVavel. That's not when you come
back to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. That's the Torah sages that go
to בבל Bavel from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael שעושים ציצים ופרחים לתורה,
she'osim tzitzim ufrachim laTorah, that they make like flowers and, you know,
buds for the Torah. So actually it's a very positive thing. They
dress nicely, appropriately as a Torah scholar should. And last one. מפני
מה עובדי כוכבים זוהמים? Mipnei ma ovdei kochavim zohamim? And why the
non-Jews have the smell? שלא עמדו על הר סיני. shelo amdu al
Har Sinai. Not because they eat non-kosher food, but they didn't stand
on הר סיני. Har Sinai. שבשעה שבא נחש על חוה, shebesha'ah sheba
nachash al Chava, because when the snake had intercourse with חוה, Chava,
which is a rabbinic, you know, מדרש Midrash that the snake had
intercourse with חוה, Chava, הטיל
בה זוהמא, hitil bah zohama, he put in her a stench. ישראל
שעמדו על הר סיני Yisrael she'amdu al Har Sinai פסקה זוהמתן. paska
zohamatan. When we stood at הר סיני Har Sinai then that, the
רש"י Rashi says the same way we were healed from all of
our other illnesses according to the מדרש, Midrash, we were also healed
from this. עובדי כוכבים שלא עמדו על הר סיני, Ovdei kochavim shelo
amdu al Har Sinai, they who did not, לא פסקה זוהמתן, lo
paska zohamatan, it did not end. Let's just finish this up. אמר
ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי Amar lei Rav Acha brei
d'Rava l'Rav Ashi גירי מאי? geirei mai? How about converts? Right? They
weren't at הר סיני, Har Sinai, so how did that stop? אמר
ליה Amar lei אף על גב דאינהו לא הוו, af al gav
d'inhu lo havu, even though they personally weren't there, you know, their
or their forebears weren't there, מזלייהו הוו, mazlaihu havu, their מזל mazal
was there. So somehow their spiritual presence was there even if their
forebears were not. דכתיב את אשר ישנו פה Dechtiv et asher yeshno
poh and that somehow carried over so they don't have the stench.
את אשר ישנו פה עמנו עומד היום לפני ה' אלהינו ואת אשר
איננו פה, et asher yeshno poh imanu omed hayom lifnei Hashem Elokeinu
v'et asher einenu poh, even though they're not physically here, it's here
too. ופליגא דרבי אבא בר כהנא. Upliga d'Rabbi Abba bar Kahana. This
idea that the stench only stopped at הר סיני Har Sinai argues
on רבי אבא בר כהנא. Rabbi Abba bar Kahana. דאמר רבי אבא
בר כהנא Damar Rabbi Abba bar Kahana עד שלושה דורות לא פסקה
זוהמא מאבותינו, ad shlosha dorot lo paska zohama me'avoteinu, that actually it
stopped way before הר סיני, Har Sinai, it stopped after three generations
of אברהם Avraham being chosen. So three generations, אברהם הוליד את ישמעאל,
Avraham holid et Yishmael, so that was not yet fully free from
his, you know, non-Jewish background if you would. יצחק הוליד את עשו,
Yitzchak holid et Esav, and only finally יעקב הוליד יב שבטים שלא
היה בהם שום שמץ. Yaakov holid Yud-Beis shvatim shelo haya bahem shum
shemetz. דופי. dofi. So by יעקב, Yaakov, we had removed ourselves from
our previous background and that already at that stage the זוהמא zuhama
ended. Okay. That sounds
like a
very nice דרוש. drush.
I'm wondering if you could maybe just elaborate slightly more on what
you meant earlier when you talked about being essentially distinct, because the
way I've been thinking about this recently is we don't hold of
essentialism in other aspects, like in our biological understanding of the world,
we don't believe in species essentialism anymore, we know that biology is
a constant fluid process and things just change, so why would we
maintain essentialism when it comes to the Jewish people? Or maybe I'm
misinterpreting what you mean by essentialism. Yeah, it's a good question. Let's
start with what the source of it is. When we say the
Jewish people are different, what does that mean? Does it mean that
we have different DNA? Obviously not. Does it mean that we have
a different soul? What does that even mean? So let's look at
it from a תורה Torah perspective and then from a philosophical perspective.